Hi. Welcome back to the Lam Rim.
Today we're going to do a review of the whole course.
It's good for me. I would like to do a review myself.
This format of doing separate episodes
and then doing them at separate times
you kind of lose the flow of the whole teaching.
I thought it would be nice today if we went back
from the beginning and we went through the flow
of the whole lam rim teaching that we had.
I'm going to do that flow based on the IDIMs, on the idea images,
that we use to teach the ACI teachers.
The ACI teachers
are expected to be able to look at one of these pictures
and identify the idea behind it.
I think, Tim how may we said there's going to be?  A thousand or something?
How many?
500, something like that. So it's kind of easy to take an exam,
to examine someone just based on the pictures.
So we just throw these pictures at you.
So I challenge you during this review
when we put up a picture
i'll give you a second and see if you
can remember what the picture was about?
Okay, and this is a good review
of the entire course that we're doing. All right, here we go...
First picture Mr. Sejii
This picture is supposed to remind you
that we are in the middle of the practices
for people of medium capacity
and what they're trying to get to is nirvana.
They're trying to get out of the wheel of life, out of all suffering for themselves personally.
This is where Buddha taught the three trainings
that will help you to reach personal your nirvana.
The third training is understanding emptiness, understanding the pen.
The second training is meditation.
On a deep level these two can only be done in a quiet place,
during certain times of the day, when you're really focusing on your meditation mat.
On a deep level,  these two have to be done
on special periods of the day.
But this one, the foundation for those two, which is being nice to other people.
You can call it morality.
You could call it an ethical way of life,
but in the end It's being nice to other people.
That's the foundation,
which is always available to us all day long.
This is one of the three extraordinary trainings of buddhism,
meant to help us to reach nirvana.
And it's available to us all day long.
So in this picture,
you can see Seiji helping Geshe Michael to figure out his computer.
Which is one of the nicest things that young people can do for older people.
Next picture; see if you can remember what this picture was?
Did you guess?
This lady is doing her taxes. What does that make her in this lam rim system?
it makes her...
a dharma master. When I say dharma master, or tantric master,
I know the picture you have in your mind.
It's a some big lama up on a throne and they have a big yellow hat.
Maybe they are ringing a bell and a little drum and they are .....
And you think; 'oh, that's a dharma master. that's a real dharma master'.
Or you're thinking of that old picture of Nagarjuna,
and he's he's all kind of mystical.
In the lam rim, what we learned
was this woman
she has a couple kids, she's married
and she's a dharma master. She is a real dharma master.
Pabongka Rinpoche said, don't think that a dharma master has to be sitting up on a throne
reciting some tantric ritual.
This lady is doing what?
She's paying her taxes.
To be honest on your taxes is like really difficult in my country.
It might take you weeks to do your taxes and
to really do them carefully,
to do them completely honestly,
to pay every single penny you're supposed to pay.
This makes her...
She has the first of the extraordinary trainings of a good person;
kind to other people.
That makes her a real dharma master.
Forget those pictures you have of lamas with big hats on,
and ringing bells. Okay, that's easy.
Anybody can do that.
To be nice to people is difficult
and to keep your morality, to keep your ethics
Is also difficult.
Next one;
I will give you a moment. Do you remember what this is about?
The quotation in the lam rim was TSUL KHRIMS LDAN PA'I DGE SLONG 'OD DANG LDAN
A person who is really keeping their vows,
really keeping their buddhist guidelines, especially the 10 guidelines,
they shine, they actually shine.
A person who is making a healthy, modest, low-key effort to keep their commitments,
to keep the ten good karmas and
be nice to other people,
they have some kind of a peaceful look on their face,
they are shining.
When they walk into a room, you know it.
Everyone starts feeling better, like Tim and Seiji.
That's a light of the world.
Buddha said, those people are the light of the world.
There's a christian expression;
don't put a candle under a basket, let the world see your happy face.
And that's a true guiding light for the whole world.
Next picture IDIM#4
This is a cliff that I went on with my partner Veronica for her birthday, during this lam rim.
They were talking about the sun setting, which in Tibetan the word is NUB PA.
It's also the word for west because the sun sets in the west;
NUB PA means
the sun setting and this is a very sad verb.
This is a very sad idea in the dharma,
The most famous place comes at the end of the Abhidharmakosha; The Treasure House of Higher Wisdom.
The Treasure House of Higher Knowledge by Master Vasabhandu, and he says;
"the sun of the dharma, the light of the dharma, will set in this world."
We will lose the light of the dharma in this world. This world will go into darkness.
After a certain amount of time,
The teachings of the Buddha will disappear in this world.
First they disappear in the minds of people but they're still in libraries.
Those books are still in libraries. Probably libraries that John Brady hasn't found yet.
And then later, they will disappear from the libraries also and then they'll be gone.
I put the picture here because Pabongka Rinpoche made a special point, he said;
'if you can't keep your commitments, if you can't keep nice behavior towards other people,
then we can say the dharma has left this world.'
The light of the dharma has left this world inside of you.
The sun has set inside your own chest,
which would be a very sad thing if we don't keep our vows.
Next picture.
We called this retreat Love in the Time of the Virus.
The point is that during a very difficult time in the world,
if you keep your commitments,
if you are nice to other people
when things are frightening and scary and the virus is spreading.
We don't know where, we don't know how, and
we don't know how many people will die.
If during those difficult times you do something nice to other people,
it's much, much more powerful.
He mentioned, if you remember, a 5-star Buddha paradise,
which is like a perfect place.
It's easy to be a good person, everybody there is a good person.
That's no big achievement.                                           That's not a big deal,
and the seed is not that powerful
to be nice in a group of nice people.
To be nice when people are attacking you, when people are afraid.
When people are not being nice to each other and to be the one person
who stands up and shares things in a difficult time -
then that's an extremely pure person.
That's a great karma. That's an incredible karma, much more powerful.
I think this virus is a very good time, and
it's a very good chance for all of us to show
- are we really buddhists?  Are we are we really practicing the bodhisattva path?
Can we help others even when things are very hard.
Next picture.
This one is hard to remember, i have trouble remembering it.
I'm going to give you a second to try to think of what this picture is.
Pabongka Rinpoche was quoting some books
with a very, very common ending to different books.
He quoted a famous one, which is BLO BZANG RGYAL BA'I BSTAN PA ... CIG
may the teachings of the victorious one
Lobsang Drakpa, Je Tsongkapa
spread in this world.
You're thinking, we got to get on the internet.
We have to translate this lamrim into many languages.
We have to try to spread the good word to as many people as we can.
That's the end of the prayer and we're supposed to walk out of this lamrim class or video
and we're supposed to share the dharma with other people.
We're supposed to spread the dharma in the world.
In this part of the lamrim, Pabongka Rinpoche said;
the place you're supposed to spread the dharma is here, inside your own heart.
Don't think that spreading the dharma means, trying to translate the videos
into more languages or something like that. That's a very important spreading of the dharma.
But he says, if you spread it in your own heart,
then of course it will spread outside of you because the world is coming from your heart,
from your heart chakra actually.
Next picture #7
Try to remember what this picture was about. I'll give you a second.
This is a favorite topic of mine;
having a personal relationship with another person, like these two people have.
In my opinion and in tantra, it's one of the happiest things that can happen to you.
It's one of the greatest things that can happen to you.
Anybody can tell you the reason the whole world is looking for a partner,
is that it makes people happy.
It's one of the greatest happinesses when it's going well.
It's one of the greatest happinesses you can have but
you know and I know when it's not going well
it's one of the greatest miseries in life.
Why is that relevant to this course right here?
If your morality is good
it's the happiest thing in your life.
And if you break your morality, it's the same thing that is going to make you miserable.
It's like having a nice woman or man, who is your partner,
the same person who makes you totally happy,
can also make you totally miserable.
So in this case, vinaya, your personal practice of kindness,
good behavior, is being compared to a partner
who can either make you be the best thing in your life
or the worst thing in your life - same person.
Next IDIM #8
This was a complicated one. See if you can remember?
I'll take a sip of my green drink.
Thanks Vimala.
This actually represents breaking your commitments.
Pulling up a weed represents breaking your commitments.
Why is destroying this plant is breaking your commitment?
If you're a gardener you know that you should pull a weed out
before the seeds are ready.
If you wait until the seeds are ready to drop off,
and then you pull the plant out
then you're going to spread about a thousand seeds.
For next next month or next year you're going to get thousands of weeds growing back.
So you have to attack those weeds early.
This refers to a very radical statement
that Buddha made
DGE SLONG DAG SROG DANG BRAL ZHING SHI BA NI BLA'I
It's better to die
than to break your vows. Why?
When you break your vows
you are setting in motion seeds
which will continue to fall off for many lifetimes.
If you die you ruin one body mind complex.
If you die you ruin one very useful temple,
a physical temple and a mind. You lose one.
But if you break your commitments
you lose many body mind complexes.
You ruin your body and mind for many lifetimes
And you kind of set seeds into motion
which are going to ruin many lifetimes.
Buddha was saying; it's better to die than to break your vows and
he was not being metaphorical. He was speaking very literally
when he said that. Better to die than to break your commitments.
There's a joke in the lamrim.
We take a vow never to give up bodhichitta even at the cost of our lives.
There's a famous statement, all through our whole life we are waiting
to get put in a prison
by some evil people.
They come up with a knife and they say' 'give up your bodhisattva vows or die today'.
Then we're gonna say;
'I choose to die'.
And they kill us.
I think all of us are waiting for this ever since we took that vow.
We're all waiting for these guys to show up with knives and  threaten us.
But actually we're the guys with the knives. We threaten our bodhisattva vows every day.
We have to make this decision every day when we decide whether or not to keep our vows carefully.
It's hard to find those guys who put you in jail, and say;
I'm going to kill you if you don't give up your  bodhisattva vows.
Next picture.
See if you can remember. I'm going to give you a minute to try to remember.
This was a reference....
we have Mixed Nuts translation team
and we were translating an old vinaya text;
monk's vows, nun's vows.
They were talking about the vow, the tradition that we shouldn't ...
...when you become a monk or a nun they give you your robes,
they give you a small buddhist statue,
and they give you a strainer.
And in ancient India you were supposed to carry this strainer around with you.
When you drink water from a stream
you're supposed to strain the water first to make sure you don't kill any small insects.
We mentioned a famous tradition in the vinaya,
if a couple of monks go down to the water,
down to the stream to get some water,
then they should choose the nicest monk to check the water.
Don't choose the guy who doesn't care about bugs. Try to find a guy who loves bugs
and have them check the water because they will be more careful.
What's the point?
We talked about kind of ecology vows,
where monks and nuns are not supposed to even pull green leaves off
a plant because these are the homes of tiny creatures.
It means, respect even the very small vows,
take them very seriously because the results multiply exponentially.
Then, it's important to keep your morality on a very subtle level,
on a very fine level and don't get anal.
If I was going to write the bodhisattva vows,
I would write an extra bodhisattva vow about
don't get anal about your bodhisattva vows.
There's nothing more irritating than
a person who informs you they are keeping their vows and
that's why they have to be an asshole today.
Keep your vows sweetly. Keep them happily. Don't overdo it.
Don't bother other people with your vows because the vows are not to bother other people.
Keep the small vows, keep them quietly. Keep them personally, don't advertise it.
There's a saying in Islam ... the left hand shouldn't let the right hand know what it is doing.
It means, don't advertise your vows. Just keep them quietly.
Keep them on a very fine level.
Next picture.
This is the idea that being nice to other people
is like planting a tree.
Today I went to PeachTree Cafe
to check on something and
me and Stanley and Allison planted a peach tree there,
when we first started the PeachTree Cafe Morning Show
And I want to tell you guys that three peaches came out this week
and we got peaches now.
What it means is, take care of your foundation practices.
Take care of the root, and plant nice karmas
by keeping your vows, by being nice to other people.
Then that's going to grow into a tree.
And that peach tree that we planted
five months ago or something,
it's already giving a lot of fruit.
If you didn't take care of it when it was tiny you wouldn't have anything.
If you take care of the foundation of your buddhist practice,
which is being nice to other people
then the fruits are going to be thousands and thousands and thousands.
It'll come, it will grow
into a huge ... it will grow into tree
it will give peaches every year and for many years you will have peaches.
Keep the....protect the ....
this child was protecting the sprout carefully.
Protect your morality.
Next picture.
If I remember correctly, there were four conditions
that might cause you to break your commitments.
If you took bodhisattva commitments
or you took vinaya pratimoksha commitments,
or even if you took diamond way tantric commitments.
I think it was four. Pabongka Rinpoche reviewed... maybe more than that ....
anyway, there were certain conditions
that would help you to break your vows.
if you want to break your vows there's a couple of special ways to do it.
Here's the first one;
which is, if you don't know what your vows are,
then that's a good way to break them. If you want to break them,
then do not study them and,
one of my pet peeves, I have many pet dharma peeves,
is teachers who give initiations, huge initiations,
and they do not explain to the people taking the initiation
that they have just taken vows.
There are hundreds of vows that you just took when you get an initiation,
and you're going to break them if you don't know them.
It's the teacher's responsibility to
train you in your vows before you get an initiation.
If they don't offer to train you, I would not take an initiation from them.
The best way to break your vows, first way, is not to know them.
Read the recipe before you start cooking.
That's what Veronica tells me every time I cook.
Next picture.
Is a lady saying, 'yeah, it's not such a big thing'.
That vow about not cutting green plants without a prayer,
come on, that's a little extreme. That's a little too much, not that important.
It is just a couple bugs
that might be using that leaf once in a while as a roof.
It's not that big of a deal.
The second great way to break your vows
is to have this attitude;
'Oh that one's not so important, I'm keeping the big ones.'
Next one.
If we get a klesha, meaning if we get some kind of negativity
running around in our mind, that's a great way to break your vows.
Getting irritated with somebody else or
getting obsessed with acquiring something or money or
getting attached to our Netflix at night.
.... by the way, it's not wrong to watch Netflix, but i'm talking about
hurting someone else because you want to get home and watch your Netflix. That's a problem.
This is called the gang fight.
The story is what?
Go for the biggest guy on the other side.
Find out who's the leader of the other side,
and don't talk, don't negotiate, don't yell at each other,
walk up to him and bash him on the head.
And then the whole other side will fall down.
Identify your worst bad habit,
and go after that one first. That's way to keep your vows.
Next one.
.... by the way at my age,
I'm not telling you how old I am,
but all this young love thing
Is so ridiculous from the point of view of my age.
I can say it with experience because I had it.
But this thing about,
Oh, she's the most beautiful woman in the world.
He's the most handsome guy in the world.
First of all, my older brother,
he said the funniest thing. He said, you like that girl? I said, yeah.
He said, you want to spend your life with her? I said, yeah.
He said, check out her mom first.
Check out how does her mom look? I said, the mom looks terrible. She's overweight, she looks tired and she looks terrible.
And he says, well, what do you think she looked like in the beginning,
So think about it?
If you're attached to the the looks of a person,
or something physical, or something not very important about a person.
That's going to change and you will see them get sick,
you will see them get old. You will see them have diarrhea and throw up.
If you're not lucky you will see their insides and in operations sometime.
Don't fool yourself
that it's worth hurting other people
to get the most beautiful woman or man that you can. It's not worth it.
It won't last. It's great to have a relationship but have it for the right reason.
Next.
If you have a problem with anger
or you get upset easily
then fantasize about giving this person
something they would love to have. This is called maitre
jampa
Love.
Fantasize, try to remember how nice it is to give someone
something they love, something they want.
Try to have this attitude.
If you don't feel friendly towards another person
then do some fantasies, which means meditation
about giving them something they really like.
Next one.
I'm gonna give you a moment for this one. I bet you can't remember what this one is?
Tim's cheating looking ahead.
What was this one?
This is about pride.
Pride is also going to be an obstacle to keeping your vows.
And ... one of the most common types of pride
in a monastic situation, which is where this book was taught generally;
is how much you know about the scriptures,  how many facts have you collected
in your lifetime.
This is something I really enjoy, is obscure dharma facts
and the more you collect
the more you feel like you are special.
Pabongka Rinpoche said, 'all the dharma you ever learned in your life, all the things you memorized,
all the things you debated,
all the geshe degrees you could ever have,
compared to what there is still left to know you don't know nothing.
You are like a worm on the bottom of the ocean,
and sometimes goes out and look up at the stars.
Many of those stars have planets around them.
There's people on those planets. There's things to know about those people.
There's the things we know,
that we're so proud about knowing,
is a tiny tiny tiny fraction of what you could know.
So don't have pride.
Next one.
One of the big motivations to break your vows
or your commitments, your morality, which is going to stop you from reaching nirvana, which is going to stop you from reaching the second
the second level of the lamrim-  personal nirvana;
is to [not?] understand emptiness, study emptiness.
If you realize, that the mean things
that someone else is doing to you,
are coming directly from what you did last week.
Then you're not gonna make big mistakes. The more you can study emptiness,
the more you can study cause and effect, dependent origination
which means this person's coming from my seeds,
then the easier it's gonna be to keep your vows. The easier it's gonna be. So study, study, study.
I had a teacher, an old inner mongol teacher, very old with tuberculosis and
he used to say,
'He's very good. You are so proud, you have such a great amount of pride from Princeton and
later the geshe thing,
that's a very helpful, very helpful...
you will push yourself harder
just to look smart.
That's lucky but later on try to give it up.
Just study to be a good person. It's very funny
He gave me Adam's text on his deathbed.
I remember this.
Next one
This is technically the fourth cause, or is it? No.
One of the causes of breaking your vows or losing your commitments.
It's very hard in the modern world
to keep your mind on your vows when you're very busy. When things are moving very fast.
There are a thousand things to see on the internet,
and life is moving so fast.
It's hard to keep that self-awareness of;
am I breaking my vows, am I doing anything to hurt someone?
You got to kind of slow down, come back to your vows
and keep some kind of awareness sensitivity
to the fact that you have commitments to not hurt other people.
The busier things get, the more careful you have to be.
It's even easy to get irritated with your partner when you're very busy.
They're trying to tell you something and
you've got 10 things going on at work and you are...
'I don't have time to listen right now.
My boss gave me 10 things to do.'
Those are the times you have to slow down
and come back to your vows.
Don't forget your commitment to be nice to other people even when you're
very stressed, very busy.
It's better to break a few business commitments than to
get nervous and stressed and be not nice to people,
it's better to not pay a bill or miss a business meeting or
not do as well as you could in your job,
if it means keeping your mind clear.
Next picture.
This is a lady buying a useless thing in the store.
See if you can remember this story.
She said, 'oh this box is so beautiful.' She went to the department store. She bought this .....
.... what's that home store thing, the
place you buy stuff? Crate and Barrel.
She went to Crate and Barrel in America. She said, 'oh my husband's gonna love this box.'
She doesn't have any clue what she's gonna use it for
but she's gonna take it home.
Then when she gets home her husband's gonna say, 'are you crazy, this is a worthless little box.
We have enough junk in our house. Take it back. Get your money back.
Should she go to the gas station and try to give it back?
No, that's not where she got the box from. It's kind of obvious but we have to say it.
If you buy a stupid box,
because you like it and you think your husband's gonna like it, which he won't...
And he talks you into taking the box back.
Don't take it back to a different place. Take it back to where you bought it.
What's that mean?
You guys should pay me.
When it's time to confess,
when you broke a vow,
then try to get back to the person who gave you the vow.
Try to confess in front of the person who gave you the vow.
Is it okay to confess at home by yourself?
Not for vows that you took from other people, in general.
If you didn't take a vow
from someone else, then maybe it's okay at home
to confess in front of a Buddha statue or something like that in in extreme cases it's alright.
But in general,
if you can get back to the person who gave you your vows
and confess to them openly - be shameless. We are shameless all day.
So be shameless about your vows, and say 'what the hell'
go straight to your teacher and say I broke this stupid vow.
And your teacher's 'wow, you're a really bad person.' You're like, yeah, yeah.
Get it over with, and then you feel so clean, you feel so nice.
You can be shy about lots of things in your life, but don't be shy about your vows.
If you break a vow go tell somebody
and that's why you get rid of it. You get rid of the problem.
If you hold it and hide it, and if you spend more work hiding it than confessing it
or keeping it, then it's just dumb
and you won't feel nice. You won't feel clean.
Just be open with your teachers. I have this problem. I have this bad habit.
The karma gets crushed, the seed gets crushed.
Your teacher's gonna say, "I heard that before, you told me before." But be persistent and keep telling them.
Next picture
This is about .....wait do you remember?
Again, this is about honoring
the small details of vows.
It's actually a vow for monks, they should brush their teeth,
with a stick that was called a SO SHING
it was a stick that you were supposed to use to clean your teeth,
you just cut it off a tree and you use it.
It's a toothbrush.
It said, monks should have their toothbrushes and you should brush your teeth.
It might seem like a small thing;
"wait, i'm trying to keep my tantric vow to go to Amitabha's  paradise
and protect all living beings and Buddha says, 'yeah, but in the meantime,
could you just please brush your teeth every day.
You think, but that's not a really big vow.
But it's the small things that make the buddha paradise.
It's the small things that bodhisattvas do,
that are nice to other people.
Of course, everybody in the world is gonna ...
... stop a nuclear war or something if they can. I mean, that's obvious.
But are you a good enough person
that you don't even want people to smell your breath
If it might hurt them?
If you're very sensitive
about tiny things that might hurt other people
then we can say you're keeping your morality.
And then it's the small details that put the finishing touches
on your buddha paradise, which you see in the next picture.
This person decorating a Christmas tree ...
If you have ever done a Christmas tree, but those of us who grew up in christian tradition
our parents had us do Christmas trees.
There's something cool about
putting on the last ornament.
Everybody's looking at the tree and they say, 'is it done' and they say, 'yeah, it's done'.
He said, 'wait, there's one more we should put right there'.
This Christmas tree ornament
is the brushing your teeth. It's the small final details
that you put on your buddhahood. It's the small things that make Buddhas.
It's not the grand things. It's not the big things. It's attention
to the small details
of making other people happy that creates a buddha.
Next one.
See if you remember this one. I'll give you a clue - yamantaka, yamantaka.
This is a famous lamrim story.
Monks and nuns are supposed to go twice a month to sojong and confess
the mistakes we made, to each other
and openly.
The teacher said,
...they struck the ?gunty. They struck the ?gunty
which is a special piece of wood, it looks like a 2x4
and you hit it with a another stick and it goes thunk, thunk, thunk...
and that's an ancient bell before before metal was common.
They will hit the plank, and when you hear that
you have to go to sojong. They still do it.
I made a ? with my teacher. He wanted one
and we made it to the right dimensions.
There's all these rules about it.
When you hear the ?
you're supposed to .... you hold it here..
you hold the ? here and you hit it like this.
Then all the monks and nuns are supposed to come for confession.
This teacher said, 'hey, they struck the ?gunty. Let's go.'
The students said, 'no i'm not going to confess today.'
The teacher said, 'what?'
That's one of the main commitments of a monk, to go to sojong.
The teacher said, 'what are you talking about?' He says, 'I don't have to go today.'
The teacher said, 'what do you mean you don't have to go today?'
He says, 'did you forget, you gave me a yamantaka initiation yesterday?
I am yamantaka, I'm a buddha. I don't need to go to sojong anymore.'
The teacher grabs him by the ear, he says, 'What the hell, you're yamantika?
Yamantika is going to sojong with me right now.'
What it means is, don't give me this stuff that you're a great tantrika,
and you're beyond morality and
now you have higher vision -
that's a completely mistaken idea!
If you got a secret initiation
then you should be going to sojong every morning or something.
You should go more than other people.
Because that's what gives you ...
gives power to your tantric practice. It's being nice to other people
and confessing when you make a mistake.
Next.
This is a sad image. We always think of morality as being the roots
of our practice,  the foundation of our practice.
Pabongka Rinpoche, kind of flipped it around.
This is a perfect picture.
He said, imagine an apple tree
that someone sliced it in half. Actually, he used a palm tree.
Somebody sliced it and they cut the top off the tree.
So you're not going to get leaves,
even a single leaf is not going to come out.
Therefore, you are not going to get flowers.
Therefore, you're not going to get the fruits which always come from the flowers.
You're not going to get anything.
A person who is not nice to other people day to day, hour to hour,
they chop off any chance
of getting those beautiful fruits of practice.
Next one.
This was an idea of something that my teacher asked me...
Sorry, that I asked my teacher and I don't know if you remember but I asked him.
The first of the five paths, the path of accumulation,
you reach it when you have a personal tragedy,
but if you're on the bodhisattva track,
you reach it when you get bodhichitta.
I said, I don't understand what's tragic about bodhichitta?
And he said, 'no no, no.
It's still a theme of tragedy.
It's just the tragedy of every being alive, every being in this whole universe
is having the same tragedy.'
That communal tragedy is the beginning of  the five paths.
Thinking about that tragedy
is the beginning of the five paths for a bodhisattva.
So really, it's the same.
The puppy's having a hard time, but now all the puppies in the basket are having a hard time.
We're all in this together.
And that's the beginning of bodhichitta.
Next picture.
This is a guy shaking hands with somebody in their office.
I imagine the lady is introducing them. This is Joe, he works in the advertising department
and this is Sam, he works in the computer department.
They shake hands.
Do you remember what this is?
It was a very, very cute exercise where we were supposed to close our eyes
and think of the person who irritates us the most.
And see if we could get ourselves upset. The problem with this kind of exercise
is after about 10 minutes you forget it's an exercise.
You really do get upset!
Let me see if I can get myself upset.
How are you going to do it?
I am going to think about this guy who gave me a hard time this week. 'Okay, go ahead'.
Then slowly the person starts shaking. You say, 'What's going on?"
I got upset. The experiment worked.
If it's your lama, they'll say,
'check out how it feels when you first start thinking about this person.'
How does it feel? What comes up in your heart?
I don't know about you, but I get this little glitch in my heart.
I start to feel some kind of discomfort here or here.
When I think about a person who's been bothering me or a problem that's been bothering me,
I can purposely generate tension
inside of myself.
He says, 'let's do an exercise - try to trigger some tension in your heart,
then look at that tension and get to know it, as if you are shaking hands with somebody.
Get to know what it feels like
when a mental affliction, negative emotion
Is first coming up in your heart and keep practicing it.
As soon as you feel better, and you forgot about this person,
then think of them again.
See if you can get upset again.
See if you can start to get upset again.
Try to get familiar with what it feels like; shake hands 'Hi. This is Geshe Michael'.
Hi. What's what's your name?
'I am starting to get upset about this person'.
'Nice to meet you. Now I know what you look like.
Now I can look out for you. I can avoid you in the future'.
Next one.
It's called visiting the middle of the sun.
The theme of this lamrim, which was Love the Time of the Virus.
The virus is a big thing, it's spread across this whole world.
I have lived a long life and I thought I saw everything.
I entered my 60s and thought now nothing new is going to happen.
I'm pretty set for anything that would happen.
I've seen everything and nothing can upset me too much. Then this virus shows up and threatens everybody in the world.
Wow, that's a big thing, that covers the whole planet.
I don't know if it happened to you, but it happened to me.
It's probably bad deed number nine, which is ill will;
being happy when someone else has a problem.
When I heard that famous, irritating, people were getting sick.
I didn't want them to die or anything, but...
... i told you it was bad to be bad.
And then I caught myself thinking like that.
It feels like a big thing.
It feels like this problem has spread all over this planet.
It feels like it is something that is difficult for me to cope with.
We have just entered,
after 10 years of lamrim study,
we have just entered the path for people of greater capacity.
We're going to open that study
with the idea of bodhichitta. What is bodhichina?
It's not enlightenment mind. Forget that lousy translation, incredibly bad translation.
It's the wish that I could become a buddha to help countless living beings.
There is a direct experience of it
in the same way that there's a direct experience of emptiness.
There are parallel experiences that
we must get to in this lifetime and again, you should be in meditation.
We describe an extraordinary.... what do you call it....breakthrough..
A threshold experience
where you go into a deep state of meditation.
Because time and space are coming from seeds,
if you can mess with these seeds,
then you can compact time and space.
In a meditation that's not longer than a half hour.
You could actually visit
each person in the universe
including animals and bugs and birds and fish.
You could communicate with each one individually,
within a half an hour.
To each one you could make a commitment.
You meet them, you see each one is suffering,
each one is having a difficult life and worried about the future.
You could go to each one separately and say,
"I got it covered, take it easy."
I used to work when I was in the university.
I got a scholarship, but they said you have to work a few hours a week.
It turned out to be 30 hours a week.
I had to drive a truck.
Actually, first they put me in a cafeteria and they said you're going to mop the floor in the cafeteria.
I quit within 10 hours. I quit on the first day.
Then they said, you can drive a truck. I said, that's fun. I'll drive a truck.
I drove a truck for five years.
We had a guy,
a permanent university employee, named Big John.
His name was Big John. He's a polish guy, seven feet tall, huge guy.
Everyone was afraid when they saw him.
They're afraid of him, but he was extremely sweet.
He would bring donuts to work and he was from Trenton, New Jersey.
He would do the nicest things for us and he would cover for us.  One day we broke a truck in half.
We hit a tree with the truck and we broke it in half.
He covered for us, 'oh these screws weren't very tight
I don't know what happened. The truck fell apart. Don't blame these guys.
Don't blame these young guys.
All they did was drive it.
Then he winked at us and said, "I got you covered. I got you guys covered."
I always think of him when I think of bodhichitta.
You're gonna meet each living being in the universe directly.
And you're going to say, "Big John has you covered. I got you covered. Don't worry."
Don't worry about it. I got you covered.
That's bodhichitta. You should have that experience.
You should work for that experience. You have to meditate.
You have to study about bodhichitta.
You have to study the lamrim about bodhichitta.
You have to do all those steps;
exchanging yourself and others...
One day you will have that experience and you will meet every living being.
You will say to them, 'I got you covered'. Don't worry. I got you covered.'
Big Mike is taking care of you or Big Tim or a Big Seiji.
Don't worry.
Don't stress out. I'm on it!
That's exactly what it feels like. It's a personal commitment.
Why are we talking about that?
You're gonna do that on countless worlds. When you do it, on the day you do it,
you will do it on countless worlds.
An action which is committed directly with every living creature on countless worlds,
doesn't have trouble taking care of a single virus on a single world.
It's nothing.
A virus that endangers
7 or 8 billion people is nothing compared to bodhichitta.
We said, if you spill ketchup on your shirt
and you deliver that shirt to the middle of the sun that's 25 million degrees Fahrenheit,
probably the ketchup stain is going to disappear.
You probably don't have to worry about the ketchup stain. Work on your bodhichitta.
You will destroy the virus, by the way, by accident.
Not a big thing.
Next picture.
Don't mess around with other paths.
Learn bodhichitta. Learn to have this experience.
Don't waste your time.
Don't focus on other things. Focus on bodhichitta.
Then you don't have to do things twice.
We talked about doing things twice. This lady's in a rush.
She says, I don't have time for this bodhichitta stuff.
I'm gonna go straight into tantra.
You're still going to have to come back and pick up that thing you forgot,
which is bodhichitta.
Work on your bodhichitta first.
You don't have to drive back home and pick up the bodhichitta and come back.
Then this was a radical example in the next picture.
This is a hard one to remember. I'm going to give you a second to think about it.
I don't know if you remember this.
This is kind of complicated.
A group of 60 guys and girls were about to achieve nirvana just by seeing emptiness directly and
without bodhichitta, it's  lower nirvana.
Manjushri shows up and teaches them about bodhichitta.
Maybe he taught about this experience we just talked about.
They were all irritated by Manjushri. They're like, don't waste our time.
We are close to nirvana. We can feel it. We can taste it.
We all saw emptiness already, don't waste our time.
Don't talk to us about this stuff.
Because they had disrespected a teaching on bodhichitta,
they went the hells.
They didn't get to nirvana. They dropped to the hell realms.
And but they burned it off
and they became humans again after many millions of years.
Deep down inside was this teaching that Manjushri had given them about bodhichitta and they remembered it.
They got to be bodhisattvas and they became buddhas.
That would take less time, than
going into a lower nirvana without studying bodhichitta.
It would be faster to go to hell
and come back
and start over again with bodhichitta,
then if you didn't use bodhichitta
and you went to a lower nirvana.
This is a picture of somebody sending somebody the wrong way on purpose.
This lady is asking;
Where is that superhighway that goes to the store I want to visit?
The guy knows the highway is blocked.
He tells her, 'don't go that way the highway's blocked. Go the other way.
And she insists, 'no,
tell me where's the highway I want.'
Then he lies to her,
and says, 'take this way it's actually the long way that he wanted her to go anyway.
This is a story about skillful means.
Next picture.
This is warming up before you run a race.
Usually, we use this image about what? Do you guys remember?
It's a breath meditation.
Usually, we say breath meditation is just warming up. Don't think it's the race.
They don't have in the olympics a contest for stretching before the race.
There's no such thing, you don't get a gold medal for stretching.
In this case, we're not talking about breath meditation. We're talking about,
it is good to do the three principle paths in order.
Get sad about this world.
Struggle to have that bodhichitta experience directly.
See emptiness so you can help everybody.
Warm up with the first feelings of sadness about this life.
Next picture.
We're almost done. I think we are very close. Are we close? Not that close. Okay
Do you remember who these guys are they are a very lousy band.
I guess you meet them in shopping malls or something, singing bad songs.
They're called, 'the opening act '.
The steps of the path for lesser capacity;
trying to get to a higher rebirth.
The steps of the path for medium capacity,
trying not to come back to this world at all.
The steps of the path for greater capacity.
These two levels are just the opening act
This is the main thing, getting to bodhichitta. What's above bodhichitta?
There's six perfections. Check it out;
steps of the past to keep your rear end
out of the lower hells, steps of the path to get to nirvana,
and then we got bodhichitta.
This experience of meeting every living being
and making a commitment that I'll take care of you.
Up here is the sixth.
This is six in Chinese.
Up here Is the six perfections.
Now, which of these is the big thing?
Which is the real band? Which is the opening act?
These guys obviously, lower nirvana not such a big deal.
What's interesting is, Pabongka Rinpoche says,
that experience
with every living being
is the is the main act.
That's what I want you to focus on.
I want you to try to have that experience.
If you have that experience we can talk about the six perfections
including number six, which is seeing emptiness.
Let's talk about that later.
Come on, I want you guys to focus on having this experience.
By the way, a good way to have that experience is to imagine that experience and try listen to the description of it.
Pretend you can do it and keep pretending.
Keep doing it.
It feels like a slot machine.
I like to say, it feels like a slot machine.
When you push a slot machine,
these pictures roll up;
cherries, and other things.
Not that I ever played a slot machine.. Well once, with my dad.
You push the lever and then these dials come like this.
Just imagine that
your mother's face comes up.
You say, 'mom you look worried'. She's like, 'yeah, i'm worried about life'.
You say, don't worry Big John has got you covered.'
Just calm down. I got it. i'm on it
Then your dad's picture comes up.
Not just the picture, but the person comes up.
It feels like that in meditation. Try to imagine it. Try to practice it.
It will trigger the real thing.
It will trigger the real thing. Bring people up, one by one.
Look at how they feel.
Make a commitment. Don't worry. I got you covered. I'm on it.
Then they pass. Bring up another person.
Practice that way. You can do five or six people.
It will get faster, because time will change.
Pabongka Rinpoche is saying that's the main show.
That's the Rolling Stones.
The rest is just new bands that aren't very good.
Who is at the end? Do they have an ending act? Not usually.
Anyway, the rest is just leaving the stadium or something. Don't worry about it.
Now we crossed over into
the 10 cool things about getting bodhichitta.
We will only have time to do the  first one in this lamrim.
The first cool thing about getting bodhichitta is...
if you have been a nerdy kid
playing tennis in the school.
Your dream was to be on the team.
Next picture.
Yeah, there's Geshe Michael in the middle.
On top, not the weirdos below.
You can be on the team. It's cool to be on the team of bodhisattvas.
Work to be on that team.
It's so cool to be on that team
because that team stretches across the universe.
It's all the cool people in the whole universe. It's nice to be part of that team.
It's sweet.
That was the first benefit of bodhichitta.
Next picture.
This is a guy visiting an art museum.
He talked about the two levels of tantra; first level meet angels,
second level study from them how to be an angel and become an angel.
In the first level,
we're supposed to actually meet
real angels in person.
It's not like standing in an art museum and looking at a statue or a thangka of a person.
It's meeting the person directly and that's totally a completely different thing.
If you try to practice tantra
without that bodhichitta experience then it will be like looking at pictures of buddhas
instead of meeting buddhas.
They don't like to talk to people who don't have bodhichitta.
They feel more comfortable
around people who have had this experience. Try to have this experience.
Then tantra is going to work for you.
If you don't have this experience
tantra is going to be difficult.
It's going to be like looking at pictures of buddhas instead of hanging out with buddhas.
Next one.
If you try to practice tantra without bodhichitta you might have bad results.
We talked about the first nuclear test
in modern times.
The scientists admitted that this explosion
might start the whole world on fire
They were just trying to do something cool.
But they were taking a chance of a huge disaster.
That's tantra without bodhichitta.
That's like setting the whole sky on fire by accident. You will mess up.
Next one.
Even small neutral karmas
become powerful for a person with bodhichitta.
A person with bodhichitta can feed a bird,
make a prayer about it
and it affects millions of people. They have this power.
Next picture.
Even small bad deeds like stealing a french fry to give it to a bird could be powerful if done by a bodhisattva.
But it's dangerous practice. We are not at that level. We are not at that level. We are not at that level
Did you hear that? No?
We had a picture
of a fugu fish.
People in Japan, like macho guys they eat this fish.
It has very, very poisonous parts of it that can kill you immediately. 50 people a year die in Japan.
But people still go to the restaurant. To serve this fish in a restaurant
you need three years of special training or you will kill somebody.
That's the same with stealing a french fry to give it to a bird
because you want to help the bird.
We're not at that level. Don't try to eat fugu fish if you are not trained.
Then we had a nice picture of Nick and Erin
with their big boss
which is Amalie.
Amalie represents the Buddha,
and Nick
represents the father
which is bodhichitta and Erin represents wisdom,
which is the direct perception of emptiness.
In a certain way,
somehow, I don't know what this belief is in Asia, but in a certain way the dad is irreplaceable.
Something special about the dad.
I don't know what it is. But anyway...
Emptiness you can see on different levels,
on all three tracks.
But bodhichitta, you got to be a special person.
You can only see it on the highest track.
It defines you
as a higher track person.
You need both to have your baby which is Buddhahood.
Next picture.
We said ?
Which Tim correctly identified today.
What's your main practice?  What's the thing that's number one in your life right now?
Until the next lamrim, the Medicine Buddha lamrim..
....I want you guys to treat this as your main practice.
Try to have that experience of meeting countless beings.
Try to have that experience.
I don't care iIf you sit there hour after hour and nothing happens,
just try, just pretend.
Go over it in your mind until the next lamrim.
Let's make a deal like that. Make it your main practice.
Next picture.
If that practice wasn't so important then one of the greatest buddhists of all time Lord Atisha would not have sailed for
13 months at the risk of his life to get the teachings on
bodhichitta that you just got
on this video. And you didn't have to go anywhere.
If Atisha thought it was worth risking his life for 13 months
in a tiny ship
on the Pacific ocean and the Indian ocean, then maybe
it's important, maybe it's worth it.
Next picture.
I think the dumbest thing you can do in your whole life is to go to Paris and not buy a croissant.
Okay. I'm just saying, probably there's other dumb things you can do in your life.
But to me the ultimate dumb thing
is to go to paris and not go to a ? At least
buy a crepe
on the street
with .... what's that chocolate stuff?
Nutella, yeah.
Don't have a nutella crepe.
Go to paris and don't have a nutella crepe, then that proves you are like crazy.
If you are studying lamrim,
if you got this far in the lamrim, and Geshela has been teaching it for 10 years,
you finally get to the croissant,
which is the bodhisattva experience.
Don't be crazy and leave Paris without eating it. Don't leave lamrim without getting this experience.
You'd be an idiot.
We're finished with a croissant. I think you want to make a presentation?
No, I was guessing there might be a croissant in that bag?
Tim Lowenhaupt
is going to make a formal presentation
to Geshela, my payment,
Oh, it's a pande? What do you call it?
What's that called?
Pande chocolate Here you gotta split it into three parts.
And give me all three, I mean no, just one.
I got the panda chocolate.
This is what you give to your teacher when they teach you about bodhichitta.
Let's make a deal.
For the next couple of months
work on that experience. Do the dedication chapter in your meditation of Shantideva.
Try to work on having that experience. The worst thing that can happen, that at least
you will plant seeds in your mind to have the experience.
Just pretend.
Just sit down and fantasize about it. Fantasizing is good meditation.
Fantasize that you had this experience of meeting,
one by one,
every living being.
You make a personal commitment with each one
to take care of them in an ultimate way,
All right. See you in the next lamrim for Medicine  Buddha. Yay!